So you ever listen to a song and think,
"This song's fine and all, but..."
"...it could really use some more jazz harmony."
Don't worry. We have all been there,
So,
...in this video, we're going to be counting down
Starting from the most basic,
...going to the most extreme.
And the way we're going to do that
...is we're going to reharmonize a simple pop melody:
...in D minor.
This is what the original sounds like:
It sounds pretty good to me, but...
...even with that nice E♭/F in the second measure,
...that's not really jazz.
This is what the jazz version would sound like.
This
...is Jazz Harmony: Level 1.
So this is a fairly typical jazz chord progression.
We're not using the basic triads anymore,
...but we're using richer 4-note seventh chords,
...like the first chord:
The next chords
...aren't in the key of D minor;
...they're
But that's okay,
...because they're the 2nd chord
...and 5th chord
...of the key of B♭,
...and they resolve to a
These
...are really the meat and potatoes of jazz harmony.
There are a vehicle for tension and release
...and create a sense of forward momentum
that gets us from one chord to the next.
This sequence is rounded out by an
...with
...chords of the parent key of D minor.
If we take a look at how the roots in this progression
...move on the circle of 5ths,
...we see that even if we skip around a little bit,
...things generally cycle stepwise to the left.
This is fairly typical of the patterns
that are found in jazz harmony.
Okay, so now that we have the basics covered,
...how do we get to Level 2?
Okay, so now we have a little bit more color,
...and the way that we got that was through
...where we take a dominant 7th chord
...and replace it with another dominant 7th chord
...3 whole steps away.
The tritone sub ends up having two of the
same notes of the chord that it's substituting.
The important 3rd and 7th degrees of the chord,
...which happened to form a tritone.
These chords had a fair amount of tension
...because they're generally non-diatonic.
They aren't from the key,
...like, for example, this B7 chord.
These chords release that tension
...by resolving down by a half step
to a chord that IS from the key,
...like this B♭6 chord.
A rich vocabulary of 7th chords that create the sense of
...is really what this level of jazz harmony is all about.
A lot of classic jazz from the 1950s
...can be said to exist primarily on this harmonic level,
...like, for example:
These artists were deeply influenced by the melodic
and harmonic choices of earlier bebop musicians,
...like, for example, Charlie Parker.
A lot of the harmonic vocabulary
of this music exists in this level.
It is the bread
...and butter
...of jazz musicians everywhere.
But, to quote Miles Davis,
...if we're going to level up,
...we have to NOT play the butter notes.
Alright, so there is definitely some
more spice happening here.
And the reason for that is jazz harmony
often uses what are called 'extensions'.
In Western music, we build different kinds of chords
...by stacking different kinds of 3rds
...on top of one another.
This is called:
We can extend chords through chord extensions
...by over-stacking thirds up and up
...without changing the basic identity of the chord.
At the core of it though, these
chord progressions are just
...colourful versions of the
meat-and-potato II-V progressions.
They're just...
...dressed up in fancy clothes,
...like, for example,
...this A7(♭9#11♭13) is just
...an A7 chord, but like...
...wearing a gaudy hat or something.
This level is perfect for big bands,
...where you have a lot of different musicians
available to play a lot of different extensions.
Artists like, of course,
...and later,
...created dense and rich layers of
harmony with their orchestras.
Now, in order to reach the next level,
...we kind of have to leave the II-V progression behind.
We have to move away from the
meat and potatoes of jazz harmony
...and get into something
...a little crunchier.
Okay.
So this was something called a
...where you have the same note that occurs
across all the chords in a progression,
...usually in the bass.
This pedal point grounds us in the key of D.
And because of that,
...the chords changing on top
don't have to be functional.
In other words, they don't have to
point to anywhere in particular.
They don't have to have that same
sense of tension and release.
Instead, you can pick and choose basically whatever
...so long as it doesn't clash with the melody.
A lot of modal jazz from the 1960s existed on this level,
...especially with the piano-playing of McCoy Tyner
with John Coltrane on albums like:
...and
This sort of style paved the way
for the next level of jazz.
Okay, now we're getting spicy.
We've now entered the wonderful world of
At this level,
...chords don't need to point to
any particular key or chord.
They just exist as
...islands rising up from the seabed of harmony,
...unconnected from one another.
For example, if we take a look at
...the second chord in the progression,
It's not in the key of D minor,
...nor does it point to any particular key.
One way to think about it
...is that this chord is not the
...of any other chord.
It exists purely because
...the melody note C works well with the chord
...because it's the chord's
By the time we've reached level 5,
...musicians just aren't formalizing
their harmonic choices as much.
Instead, they're pretty much relying
purely on their experienced ears
...to guide them with their aesthetic decisions.
Now, by the late 1960s,
...the jazz avant-garde
...largely abandoned harmony as a
guiding principle in composition.
But you could still hear Level 5 harmony in albums like
...by Miles Davis.
These Level 5 albums would greatly
influence the harmonic choices
...of later fusion artists like Herbie Hancock
...and Chick Corea.
So, now that we can basically use whatever
weird chords we want and call it jazz,
...where can we possibly go from here?
Well:
ʷᵗᶠ ʷᵃˢ ᵗʰᵃᵗ
This level is the spiciest of them all.
Level 6 is the land of
...basically anything and everything that
...used
...now we can use in jazz harmony.
So let's take a look at this
...B♭m(maj7) / Fmaj7 / C#5.
We have three unrelated chords
...stacked on top of one another,
...each conflicting in various ways.
For example,
...the G# of the C#5
...creates a minor 9th
...with the A of the Fmaj7,
...which in turn creates another minor 9th
...with the B♭ of the B♭m(maj7).
These overtones
...are at war with one another.
It's a dramatic and intense moment.
And because of that, it should be used quite sparingly.
As Ludmila Ulehla would write in her book
So just like Ghost Peppers,
...Level 6 jazz harmony should be used extremely rarely
...and in very small doses,
...otherwise it might ruin a perfectly good dish.
Examples of Level 6 harmony
...might be Bob Graettinger's arrangements
for the Stan Kenton Orchestra's album
...or maybe
...anything by David Liebman.
He's a spicy boi.
So, now we have jumped completely off the deep end.
How are we supposed to get to the final level?
Oh Miles Davis,
...Prince of Darkness,
...show us the way.
Show us how to not play the butter notes.
Show us the way to Jazz Level 7.
Alright, so what is going on here?
Well, this is an example of
...where the chords have been tuned to the melody.
So, the melody has stayed
...in our normal 12-tone equal tempered system
...that we all know and love,
BUT
...the chords have been tuned to
...just intonation ratios,
...based on the harmonic functions
...of the melody notes that they're paired with.
For example,
...the G here on this Am7
...is the minor 7th of the chord.
Now, there are different just intonation
ratios that can be used for minor 7ths,
...depending on the context.
But this one used a
This 9/5 ratio happens to be about
...18 cents sharp from its equal-tempered counterpart.
So, to compensate,
...the chord has to be detuned by 18 cents
...just to make sure that the G of the
melody is still in equal temperament.
That's the basic idea behind the process.
We tune the just-intonated chords
to the equal-tempered melody.
But some interesting things can happen
...when we use different ratios for the same interval.
For example,
...we could use
...for G on this A7#9.
7/4 is 33 cents flat from its equal-tempered counterpart,
...so we have to tune the whole chord UP 33 cents
...to keep the G of the melody in equal temperament.
Think of the roots for both of these chords as 'A', but
...because the minor 7ths are defined differently
...and G stays the same in the melody,
...the root notes are almost exactly a quarter tone apart.
We could say that Level 7 jazz harmony is
It exists outside of the realm of our
normal 12-tone equal tempered system.
These tuning shenanigans are
how Jacob Collier, of course,
...famously modulated to
...in his arrangement of 'In the Bleak Midwinter'.
But other artists like Steve layman
...have experimented with this sort of
thing with his spectral compositions.
What's interesting is that
...this harmony can be very subtle, as you heard,
...in comparison to the bombast of Level 6.
To me though, these chords feel like nothing else.
They feel like they're almost
...piercing through at me
...rather than laying on this bed impassive.
I'm not really quite sure if that makes any sense
So, I'll play with a 12-tone equal tempered
version of these chords
...back-to-back with the intonalist version
so that you can hear it for yourself.
So it might sound a little off,
...a little out of tune, but...
...in a good way,
...to me at least.
It almost feels like that cassette-tape sort of vibe,
...that lo-fi sort of vibe.
In fact, if you slowed it down
...and just put an anime girl studying on top of it,
You'd have
...lo-fi hip-hop.
And there we go.
Just intonated chords of the Dilla beats gives us
...the 7th level of jazz harmony.
If you enjoy this video,
...check out my Patreon
...because it's my patrons over at my Patreon
that make these videos possible.
Thank you so much for watching.